Guide to the Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute Records 1970-2012 (bulk 1980-2012)
Central Washington University Archives and Special Collections
Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute Records
1970-2012 (bulk 1980-2012)
Central Washington University, Archives and Special Collections 400 E University Way Ellensburg, WA 98926 (509) 963-2244 http://www.cwu.edu/~cwuchci/ chci@cwu.edu
MS009-01-01
Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute
1618 VHS tapes; 1038 mini Digital Videocassettes; 46 16 mm film reels; 151 Betamax tapes; 72 Sanyo V-cord; 101 ½” high density tape reels; 51 U-matic tapes; 183 Super 8 film reels; 8,014 slides; 10,842 photographs; and approximately 1,000 3-ring binders of paper records 16mm film, 8mm film, ¾” U-matic, Sanyo V-Cord, Betamax, ½” open reel magnetic tape, VHS, mini Digital Videocassettes, DVD, photographic prints, negatives, slides, paper records. Paper records are in fair to good condition. Some of the media shows degradation and the film, U-matic, Sanyo V-Cords, Betamax, and open reel tape lack playback ability.
The Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute Collection contains the daily operational records concerning the care and interaction with cross-fostered and signing chimpanzees as well as the research that has been undertaken with the chimpanzees. The entire collection spans from 1970 to 2012.
Historical Note
In 1966, Beatrix and R. Allen Gardner began Project Washoe by cross-fostering (i.e. one species raising another, in this case humans raising a chimpanzee) the chimpanzee Washoe as if she were a deaf child at the University of Nevada at Reno. A vital component of the cross-fostering environment was the exclusive use of American Sign Language (ASL) in communication between Washoe and her caregivers. Raised in this environment, Washoe acquired the signs of ASL in much the same way that deaf human children acquire the signs, making her the first non-human in history to acquire a human language. In 1967 Roger Fouts entered Project Washoe as a graduate assistant and became intimately involved in the daily care of Washoe and exposing her to ASL. In 1970, Washoe, accompanied by Roger Fouts and his wife Deborah Fouts, moved to the Institute of Primate Studies (IPS) at the University of Oklahoma in Norman, Oklahoma. For the first time Washoe was able to interact with other chimpanzees. At the IPS, in addition to working with Washoe, Roger Fouts exposed other chimpanzees at the Institute to ASL.
The next step in the study was to see if a chimpanzee mother, Washoe, could transmit the acquisition of American Sign Language to an infant chimpanzee. On January 9, 1979 Washoe gave birth to a male infant, Sequoyah, and it seemed the project could move forward. However, Sequoyah suffered from a number of health setbacks during the first months of his life and ultimately succumbed to pneumonia on March 8, 1979. The opportunity to study the transmission of ASL from mother to infant was ultimately revitalized with the introduction of another infant chimpanzee, thus beginning Project Loulis (1979-1985). On March 29, 1979, Washoe was introduced to a 10 month old infant, Loulis, whose own mother was unable to care for him. During the early years of Loulis’s life, humans were restricted from signing around him. Loulis learned his signs from Washoe and from the other signing chimpanzees, making him the only chimpanzee ever to acquire a human language from a conspecific.
The Gardners' cross-fostered other young chimpanzees: Moja, Tatu, and Dar, who also acquired the signs of ASL; Moja joined Washoe, Loulis, and the Foutses in Oklahoma in 1979. By this point, Roger Fouts was looking for a new place to call home for the chimpanzees under his care and for his research. In 1980, the Foutses moved with Washoe, Loulis, and Moja to Central Washington University in Ellensburg, Washington. In 1981, Dar and Tatu joined the other chimpanzees at Central Washington University. Originally housed in the Psychology Building, the chimpanzees were relocated to the Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute in 1993 which was specifically built with their needs in mind. Roger and Deborah co-directed the Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute until their retirement in 2011. The current director, Dr. Mary Lee Jensvold, has been a member of the research team since 1986 and studied under Drs. Fouts and Gardner.
The research that continues today with the cross-fostered adult chimpanzees shows they use their signs in spontaneous, appropriate, and conversational ways with their human caregivers and each other. They sign to initiate activities, comment on their world, request, respond to questions, and clarify misunderstandings. They adjust their signing to their conversational partner, for example they slow down their signing for new signers. They sign to themselves like humans talk to themselves. They use their signs in imaginary play, for example signing to stuffed animals. They draw pictures and name the images they create.
While the main objectives of Project Washoe and Project Loulis have come to a close, the chimpanzees continue to serve as the focus of continuous research studies. Thirty undergraduates intern each academic year and participate in the daily care and enrichment of the chimpanzees. Nine graduate students per academic year work towards their Masters of Science degrees in Experimental Psychology and Primate Behavior with CHCI as their research host. CHCI also runs a Summer Apprentice program which allows students and faculty to gain experience working with the chimpanzees as well as learning the history of the project. Additionally, CHCI has played host to a number of visiting researchers, drawing both nationally and internationally, who have conducted new research as well as utilizing the over forty years of data housed on-site.
The Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute Collection contains material spanning from 1970-1980 and the time at the Institute of Primate Studies in Norman, Oklahoma, to the move of Roger Fouts and the five chimpanzees in 1980 to the campus of Central Washington University in Ellensburg, Washington, which to this day is the home of the remaining chimpanzees: Loulis, Tatu, and Dar. The collection consists of: completed, abandoned, and ongoing research (including grant-funded projects) and thesis studies; photographic negatives, prints, and slides; film and video footage in VHS, mini Digital Videocassettes, Betamax, ¾” u-matic, ½” high density tape, Sanyo V-Cord, 16mm film, and 8mm film; charts, records, and logs of daily chimpanzee care and activity. The bulk of the collection is from 1980-2012 and has originated from Central Washington University; however, the collection does contain records and media originating from the University of Oklahoma.
Funding for the production of this finding aid was provided through a grant awarded by the Lounsbery Foundation.
Arranged chronologically within each series.
All requests to use the collection must be vetted through the Friends of Washoe and the Director of the Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Fouts, Roger; Fouts, Deborah
Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute
Ellensburg (Wash.)
Washoe (Chimpanzee); Human-animal communication; American Sign Language--Study and teaching
Language and Languages; Washington (State); Moving Images; Anthropology
- Oklahoma Data, 1970-1973; I
  Data collected while at the University of Oklahoma, Institute of Primate Studies in Norman, Oklahoma. All records were created by Roger S. Fouts or by individuals working under his direction. Records are ditto copied, photocopied, and handwritten notes housed in 3-ring binders.
- 16mm Film, II
  This series includes news footage of the chimpanzees and Roger Fouts at the Institute of Primate Studies, educational films, and additional footage filmed while at the Institute of Primate Studies. The film in this series is on both acetate and polyester bases.
  - Washoe Chimpanzee, 1
  - CWU Chimpanzees, 2
  - Selected takes of Washoe, 3
  - Roger Fouts and Washoe, 4
  - Diana and Jesabel, 5
  - Roger Fouts and Ally, 6
  - Roger Fouts, Washoe, and Sequoyah, 7
  - Footage of the Institute of Primate Studies, 8
  - Apes, 9
  - William Lemmon, 10
  - Animal Communication: Debbi and Roger Fouts and Chimpanzees, 11
  - Unknown subjects, 12
- Oklahoma Art Study, 1971-1972; III
  Each folder contains pencil drawings by the chimpanzees and typed sheets with handwritten notes from their observers. The Booee folder contains a black pencil with teeth marks and the Lucy folder contains paintings with acrylics in addition to the pencil drawings.
- Super 8 Film, 1973-1981; IV
  The film in this series covers time spent at the Institute of Primate Studies and the first couple of years at Central Washington University. The film covers many of the other chimpanzees at the Institute of Primate Studies that were not under Roger Fouts’ direct care but were taught American Sign Language under his tutelage. The 8mm film in this series is on reels, Magi-Cartridges, and loose.
  - Washoe’s Birthday Party, 1
  - Booee, Bruno, and Ally signing, 2
  - Ally, 3
  - Reintroduction of infant to Washoe, 4
  - Nim and human with objects, 5
  - Mac and human with objects, 6
  - Chimp Island, 7
  - Washoe and Roger Fouts eating breakfast, 8
  - Booee signing, 1973; 9
  - Lucy signing, 1973; 10
  - Ally and Bruno, 1974; 11
  - Bruno, 1974; 12
  - Salome, 1974; 13
  - Washoe’s Labor, 1979; 14
  - Diana Davis and Sequoyah, 1979; 15
  - Carrie gives birth, 1979; 16
  - Ally and Washoe on walk, 1979; 17
  - George Kimbell, 1979; 18
  - Bob Ingersoll, 1979; 19
  - Bob Ingersoll and Loulis, 1979; 20
  - Washoe, Loulis, and Diana Davis, 1979; 21
  - Washoe and Loulis on walk, 1979; 22
  - Nim and human caregiver, 1979; 23
  - Washoe and Loulis, 1980; 24
  - Washoe and Loulis, 1981; 25
  - Washoe, Loulis, and Dar, 1981; 26
  - Unknown Subjects, 27
- ½” High Density Tape, 1974-1981; V
  During the period of time while at the Institute of Primate Studies, extensive research was being conducted on the relationships between mother and infant chimpanzees; many of these tapes come from that research. Additionally, this series includes signing interactions between chimpanzees and human caregivers as well as Debbi Fouts’ thesis data.
  - Booee and Bruno, 1974; 1
  - Booee and Ally, 2
  - Washoe, Roger Fouts, and human caregivers, 1977; 3
  - Ally and human caregivers, 1977; 4
  - Objects introduced to chimpanzees with no signing, 1977; 5
  - Direct Signing, 1977; 6
  - Chimpanzee Mother/Infant Dyads, 1978; 7
  - Washoe and Ally, 1978; 8
  - Nim with no signing, 1978; 9
  - Tes with human caregivers, 1978; 10
  - Ally and Roger Fouts, 1978; 11
  - Wendy and Woodrow, 1978; 12
  - Washoe and Ally, 1978; 13
  - Washoe, Ally, and human caregivers, 1978; 14
  - Mac and infant, 1978; 15
  - Tiger and Mary Jane, 1978; 16
  - Chimp to chimp and chimp to human interactions, 1981; 17
  - Debbi Fouts Thesis Data, 1983; 18
  - Japanese TV footage, 1983; 19
  - First Signs of Washoe, 20
  - Unknown subjects, 21
- Sanyo V-Cord Tapes, 1979-1982; VI
  This series includes recordings from the last year Roger Fouts and Washoe were at the Institute of Primate Studies as well first two years at Central Washington University.
  - Washoe’s Labor, 1979; 1
  - Washoe and Abindigo, 1979; 2
  - Washoe and Sequoyah’s reintroduction, 1979; 3
  - Washoe, Ally, and Sequoyah, 1979; 4
  - Introduction of Loulis and Washoe, 1979; 5
  - Washoe, Loulis, and Ally, 1979-1980; 6
  - Moja and Washoe, 1979-1980; 7
  - Dar interacting with human caregivers, 1981; 8
  - Chimp to chimp signing with Tatu and Loulis, 1982; 9
  - Moja Art Study, 1982; 10
  - Unknown subjects, 11
- Loulis Phrase Development Data, 1979-1998; VII
  The initial premise of Project Loulis focused on the cultural transmission of a human language in chimpanzees. After it was clear that Loulis had acquired signs that he learned from Washoe and the other signing chimpanzees, studies looked at how his phrases developed and how he used his signs in interactions with other chimpanzees and with human caregivers. The records are stored in 3-ring binders.
- Sign Logs, 1979-2012; VIII
  Observational records of a "good"/lengthy interaction, the use of a new sign, or chimp to chimp (C-C) signing. Datasheets include: Subject, Behavior, and Observer. The Loulis logs #22-29 are PCM logs which record the place, configuration, and movement of an observed sign. Records are stored in 3-ring binders.
  - All chimps, 1983-1991; 1
  - Washoe Sign Logs, 1983-2007; 2
  - Moja Sign Logs, 1983-2002; 3
  - Tatu Sign Logs, 1983-2010; 4
  - Dar Sign Logs, 1983-2003; 5
  - Loulis Sign Logs, 1979-1980; 6
  - Loulis PCM Logs, 1979-1981; 7
  - Loulis Sign Logs, 1981-2003; 8
  - Sign Logs (All), 2002-2004; 9
  - Dar and Loulis Sign Logs, 2003-present; 10
  - Tatu Sign Logs, 2010-present; 11
- Research Data, 1979-2011; IX
  - Apprentice Loulis Project, 1979-1998; 1
  - Enrichment Video Scan, 1980-1998; 2
  - Idiolect/Dialect, 1985-1996; 3
  - Dialect Play, 1986-2000; 4
  - Video Transcription, 1986-2000; 5
  - Foraging Study, 1993-2006; 6
  - Social Hierarchy, 1995-2008; 7
  - Naïve vs. Educated Study, 1996; 8
  - Behavior Study, 1997; 9
  - Party Vocabulary, 1998-2008; 10
  - Ethogram Data Sheets, 1999-2002; 11
  - Audience Effect Study, 2000-2004; 12
  - In/Out Study, 2001-2002; 13
  - Art Study Data, 2001; 14
  - Dialect-Play Segments, 2001; 15
  - Attitude Change Study, 2001; 16
  - Object Use Project, 2002; 17
  - Reassurance/Greeting, 2002; 18
  - Context Data, 2002-2005; 19
  - Nesting Project, 2003-2004; 20
  - Forage Status, 2004; 21
  - Laughter Project-Play Bout Durations, 2005; 22
  - Vocalization and Handedness Project, 2007; 23
  - Play Segments, 2007; 24
  - Hierarchy, 2001-2008; 25
  - Snuggle Buddy, 2008; 26
  - Chimposium Effects Study Data, 2008-2009; 27
  - Movement Study Data, 2009; 28
  - Hierarchy Data, 2009; 29
  - Enrichment Study Data, 2010; 30
  - Threat Behavior Study, 2011; 31
  - Conversational Turns Coding Book, 32
  - Video Transcription in Progress, 33
  - Naturalistic Signed Interactions, 34
  - Gesture Logs, 35
  - Adventitious Data, 36
  - Grooming Data Sheets, 37
  - Handedness Project, 38
  - Arm/Finger Extension, 39
- Meal Charts, 1980-2011; X
  Meal charts are records of everything the chimpanzees eat each day. Caregivers fill in the ingredients of everything they serve the chimpanzees and also how much they ate. Medicines are also indicated on the meal chart, as well as any abnormal stool notes. Male chimpanzee arousal and odor levels and female sexual swelling cycles are also noted on the meal charts. Meal charts are stored in 3-ring binders in the conference room.
- Loulis Sign Analysis, 1981-1984; XI
  Data analysis of signs Loulis used during Project Loulis. The records are housed in 3-ring binders.
- Chimp to Chimp Logs and Data, 1981-1990; XII
  Detailed diary notes and logs of chimpanzee to chimpanzee signing. The records are housed in 3-ring binders.
- Daily Logs and Sign Analysis, 1981-1985; XIII
  Detailed diary notes and sign logs from Project Loulis. Logs are housed in 3-ring binders.
- Placement, Configuration, and Movement (PCM), 1981-2001; XIV
  Charts that explain the placement, configuration, and movement of each observed sign for the five chimpanzees. The records are housed in 3-ring binders.
- Video Follow Tapes, 1981-2011; XV
  Video Follow is comprised of 15 minute focal follows. Each chimp is taped twice a day for ten days. The chimps are filmed in the order presented on the data sheet for each day. Video Follow tapes from 1981 are on Betamax; from 1986 to May 2000 are on VHS; and October 2000 to present are on mini Digital Videocassettes. Video Follow from 1981 to March 1993 took place in the Psychology Building at Central Washington University. Starting in May 1993, all recordings took place in the Chimpanzee and Human Communication Institute at CWU.
  - Video Sample Tapes, 1981; 1
  - Video Follow Data, 1986; 2
  - Video Follow Data, Spring 1992; 3
  - Video Follow Data, Fall 1992; 4
  - Video Follow Data, Winter 1993; 5
  - Outdoor Video Follow 1, Spring 1993; 6
  - Video Follow 2, Spring-Summer 1993; 7
  - Outdoor Video Follow 2, Fall 1993; 8
  - Video Follow 3, Spring 1994; 9
  - Outdoor Video Follow 4, Fall 1994; 10
  - Outdoor Video Follow 5, Spring 1995; 11
  - Video Follow 6, Fall 1995; 12
  - Video Follow 7, Spring 1996; 13
  - Video Follow 8, Fall 1996; 14
  - Video Follow 9, Spring 1997; 15
  - Video Follow 10, Fall 1997; 16
  - Video Follow 11, Spring 1998; 17
  - Video Follow 12, Fall 1998; 18
  - Video Follow 13, Spring 1999; 19
  - Video Follow 14, Fall 1999; 20
  - Video Follow 15, Spring 2000; 21
  - Video Follow 16, Fall 2000; 22
  - Video Follow 17, Spring 2001; 23
  - Video Follow 18, Fall 2001; 24
  - Video Follow 19, Spring 2002; 25
  - Video Follow 20, Fall 2002; 26
  - Video Follow 21, Spring 2003; 27
  - Video Follow 22, Fall 2003; 28
  - Video Follow 23, Spring 2004; 29
  - Video Follow 24, Fall 2004; 30
  - Video Follow 25, Spring 2005; 31
  - Video Follow 26, Fall 2005; 32
  - Video Follow 27, Spring 2006; 33
  - Video Follow 28, Spring 2006; 34
  - Video Follow 29, Fall 2006; 35
  - Video Follow 30, Spring 2007; 36
  - Video Follow 31, Fall 2007; 37
  - Video Follow 32, Spring 2008; 38
  - Video Follow 33, Fall 2008; 39
  - Video Follow 34, Spring 2009; 40
  - Video Follow 35, Fall 2009; 41
  - Video Follow 36, Spring 2010; 42
  - Video Follow 37, Fall 2010; 43
  - Video Follow 38, Summer 2011; 44
  - Video Follow 39, Fall 2011; 45
- Health Records, 1982-1993; XVI
  - Sexual swelling cycle charts for female chimpanzees, 1
  - Health and nutrition logs, 2
  - Regurgitation data, 3
- U-Matic Tapes, 1983-1989; XVII
  - Chimp to Chimp signing, 1983; 1
  - Highlights from VCR tapes, 1985-1986; 2
  - Signs of Enrichment, 1986; 3
  - Washoe Film, 1987; 4
  - Media shots, 1989; 5
  - Washoe and Loulis, 6
  - Roger Fouts Interview, 7
  - Interview with Roger and Debbi Fouts, 8
  - First Signs of Washoe, 9
  - Cleaning, 10
  - Chimpanzees in play room, 11
  - Rats, 12
  - Private Signing, 13
  - Unknown subjects, 14
- Sign Checklists, 1983-2011; XVIII
  The Sign Checklists are a daily log of all the observed signs used by the chimpanzees in a given day. The checklists include signs in which the chimpanzees are reliable as well as a place to include newly observed signs. The checklists in the Archive Room are computer printouts bound together while the rest of the checklists are organized chronologically within 3-ring binders.
  - 1983-1991, 1
  - 1992-1998, 2
  - Washoe Sign Checklists, 1983-2007; 3
  - Moja Sign Checklists, 1981-2002; 4
  - Tatu Sign Checklists, 1983-2011; 5
  - Dar Sign Checklists, 1983-2011; 6
  - Loulis Sign Checklists, 1983-2011; 7
  - Tatu, Dar, and Loulis Sign Checklists, 2011-2012; 8
- Thesis Data, 1983-2011; XIX
  - Mark Bodamer Thesis Data, Chimpanzees Signing to Themselves, 1983-1987; 1
  - Kelly O’Donoghue, The Use of Sign Language During Play, 1985; 2
  - Heidi Shaw, Chimpanzee Vocal Comprehension of English, 1989; 3
  - Shelia Steiner, Handedness in Chimpanzees, 1989; 4
  - Vicki Kennerud, The Effect of Social Context on the Use of ASL in Chimpanzees, 1992; 5
  - Kimberly Williams, Nighttime Enrichment, 1994-1998; 6
  - Kimberly Williams, Nighttime Activity Budgets, 1995; 7
  - Julia Quentin Davis, Perception of Distortions in Chimpanzee Signing, 1995; 8
  - Shannon Cianelli, High Arousal Interactions of Chimp-to-Chimp Signing, 1995-1996; 9
  - Katherine Cadish Hall, The Use of ASL in the Grouping of Colored Exemplars, 1997; 10
  - Marcee Harvey, Tool Modification, 1998; 11
  - John Blaine Mulcahy, Pre-conflict Behavior, 1998; 12
  - Crickette Sanz, Fecal testosterone and cortisol levels and behavioral correlates, 1998; 13
  - Bonita King, Effect of Familiarity on Social Interactions, 1999; 14
  - Esteban Rivas Dissertation Data, Signing Interactions, 1999; 15
  - Rivas/Davis, Conversational Turns in Chimp-Caregiver Interactions, 2000; 16
  - Adriana Martin, Effect of Human Eye Gaze on Delay in Communicative Interactions, 2000; 17
  - Lorien Vaughan, Use of High Arousal ASL During Conflict and Post-conflict Periods, 2000; 18
  - Diana Goodrich, Play Initiation, 2000; 19
  - Sarah Baeckler, Effects of Captive Management on Chimp-Caregiver Interactions, 2001; 20
  - Holly Bowman, Effects of Gestural Communication on Reciprocity, 2003; 21
  - Elizabeth Kuykendall, Questions and responses from chimpanzees, 2003; 22
  - Debbie Tierney, Responses to Questions vs. Statements, 2004-2005; 23
  - Jess Hartel, Effects of Familiarity and Signing on Conversational Behaviors, 2005; 24
  - Lisa Leitten, Conversational Repair, 2005; 25
  - Susan Shiau, Modulation of Signs by Chimpanzees, 2005; 26
  - Jennifer Keysur, Dyadic Play, 2006; 27
  - Maureen McCarthy and Tracy Campion, Gesture Sequence Studies, 2006-2010; 28
  - Lindsay Zager, Florida Visitor Effect Study, 2009; 29
  - Lindsay Zager, Visitor Behavior Data, 2009; 30
  - Gina Stadtner, Sequential Analysis Data, 2009; 31
  - Jackie Smith, Effect of Caregiver Behavior, 2009; 32
  - Gina Stadtner, Effect of Caregiver Behavior, 2009; 33
  - Debbie Metzler, Familiar and Unfamiliar Conversational Partners, 2009; 34
  - Robin Potosky, Modulation of Signs by Chimpanzees, 2009; 35
  - Madeleine Leake, Conversation Topics, 2010-2011; 36
  - Jessica Martinson, Sorting of Chimpanzee Art, 37
- Thesis and Research Tapes, 1984-2010; XX
  - Unknown Study, 1984; 1
  - CWU Chimp Lab, 1986; 2
  - C. Stevens Art Study, 1985; 3
  - Mark Bodamer Thesis Data, 1986-1987; 4
  - National Geographic Private Signing, 1986-1988; 5
  - Music Study, 1988; 6
  - Imagination Data, 1989; 7
  - Heidi Shaw Research, 1989-1995; 8
  - Shelia Steiner Thesis Data, 1989; 9
  - Mark Bodamer Dissertation Data, 1990-1993; 10
  - Parks Grant I and II Enrichment Studies, 1990; 11
  - Unknown Study, 1990; 12
  - Pilot Filming, 1990-1991; 13
  - Vicki Kennerud Thesis Data, 1992; 14
  - Abeer Nabi Thesis Data, 1992; 15
  - Directional Pointing, 1992; 16
  - Miscellaneous Tapes, 1992-1998; 17
  - Jennifer Beaucher Thesis Data, 1993; 18
  - Forage Study, 1993; 19
  - Danielle Simpson Thesis Data, 1993; 20
  - Mary Radeke Thesis Data, 1993; 21
  - Treat Mound Study, 1993; 22
  - Questions Series, M.L. Jensvold, 1993-1994; 23
  - John Fosnick Thesis Data, 1993; 24
  - Sleep Signing Data, 1994; 25
  - Quentin Davis Thesis Data, 1994-1995; 26
  - Human eye gaze reliability, 1995; 27
  - Crickette Sanz, 1995; 28
  - Dominance Study, 1995; 29
  - Nighttime Enrichment Study, 1995-1998; 30
  - Kimberly Williams Thesis Data, 1995; 31
  - Eye Gaze Thesis Data, 1995; 32
  - Trina Hall Thesis Data, 1996; 33
  - Shannon Cianelli Thesis Data, 1996; 34
  - Trina Hall Thesis Data, 1996; 35
  - Marcee Harvey TV Enrichment Study, 1996-1997; 36
  - Marcee Harvey Thesis Data, 1997-1998; 37
  - Natural Conversations, M.L. Jensvold, 1997; 38
  - Michelle Haislip Thesis Data, 1998; 39
  - Joe Hood Thesis Data, 1998; 40
  - Earthwatch Reliability Tapes, 1998-2004; 41
  - Bonita King Thesis Data, 1999; 42
  - Lisa Leitten Thesis Data, 1999; 43
  - Summer Research, 1999; 44
  - Attention Getting Study, 2000; 45
  - Lorien Vaughan Thesis Data, 2000; 46
  - A. Martin Thesis Data, 2000; 47
  - Blake Dollnes Thesis Data, 2000; 48
  - Diana Goodrich Thesis Data, 2000; 49
  - Audience Effects Reliability, 2000; 50
  - John Blaine Mulcahy Thesis Data, 2001; 51
  - Summer Play Research, 2001; 52
  - Greet and Reassurance, 2002; 53
  - Anne Sloan Thesis Data, 2002; 54
  - Loulis Cultural Transmission, 2002; 55
  - “WH” questions, 2002; 56